29-year-old John discovered a lump in
his right breast he ignored it he
thought it had something to do with
weightlifting and the lump enlarged and
he developed blood spots on his white
T-shirt he didn't think much of it but
it prompt him to go get it checked out
some important things about John to
consider he did not drink alcohol and he
had a smoking history of five pack years
he was also an obese men with a body
mass index of
3.5 after physical examination it
revealed that John had a
2.5 roughly 2.5 cm Mass located in the
inner quadrant of the right breast he
was referred out for mamography and
ultrasound and the findings reported
that JN had a three cimer mass of
irregular high density the margins were
not circumcised and ultrasound also
showed an enlarged lymph node in the
right axela measuring
1.3 cm in diameter he was referred out
for biopsy and it confirmed that JN had
invasive ductal cell carcinoma pet scan
results revealed no signs of systemic
manetic disease but this case is rather
shocking breast cancer in men accounts
for less than 1% of breast cancer
diagnoses and about one in eight women
will be diagnosed with breast cancer
according to the American Cancer Society
a whopping
27,9 women and
2,800 men will be diagnosed with breast
cancer this year in the us alone welcome
to True Health Tuesdays I'm Dr Kenisha
Reynolds a naturopathic functional
medicine physician and forensic
scientist one of my specialties is
integrative oncology in light of breast
cancer awareness month we're going to
delve into all things breast health so
that you can maintain healthy breast
tissue breast diseases are very common
in women nonpol breast diseases such as
breast cyst galactal cells and breast
pain and fibro cystic breast lump in
fact over 40% of women experience some
kind of breast pain and when we're
thinking about breast health and
maintaining healthy breast tissue we
want to assess risk factors and the goal
is to prevent cancer some of the risk
factors for breast cancer that we should
be aware of would include things such as
family history first-degree relatives
parent sibling child if it runs in a
family it can be a risk factor highly
dense breast tissue dense breast tissue
is likely to at some point develop
abnormal cells and this can create
breast cancer not to mention how
difficult it is for Imaging to actually
pick up any abnormalities if there is a
growing tumor highly dense breast tissue
is another risk factor dense breast
tissue has more cells that can become
abnormal dense breast tissue also make
it difficult for Radiologists to
identify any suspicious Mass on
mamography
Obesity is another risk factor obesity
is associated with an increased activity
of an enzyme called aromatase and breast
tissue which increases local production
of estrogen the larger you are the more
body fat you hold the more EST estrogen
you can produce and everyone knows that
alcohol consumption can be detrimental
to your health even light drinking one
drink per day is associated with an
increased risk of breast cancer
alcoholism aceto alahh which is a known
carcinogen in fact alcohol is considered
a group one carcinogen alcohol can
increase estrogen levels and alcohol
produces aceto alide which is a known
Cur percen for that reason you should
avoid alcohol the next risk factor
smoking now we all can agree that
smoking is not healthy doesn't
contribute to anything for the body in
fact cigarettes contain 7,000 chemicals
that have the ability to promote
oxidative stress and tissue damage for
that reason you do not want to smoke
cigarettes because the chemicals can
cause DNA changes mutations and that can
lead to a breast cancer delaying
childbirth yes having babies is actually
very protective Against Breast Cancer
the older a woman is when she has her
first fullterm pregnancy the higher her
risk for breast cancer women who are
older than 30 years old when they give
birth to their first child have a higher
risk for breast cancer than a woman
who's never given birth full-term
pregnancy
renders the glands of the breast less
susceptible to tumor development and
there's this thing about breastfeeding
some women don't like breastfeeding but
lactation also has a protective effect
Against Breast Cancer leading to a
reduction of 5% some women may not
necessarily like nursing baby but
lactation is protective Against Breast
Cancer with up to a 64% reduction and
risk so ladies having babies and having
them early and breastfeeding is
extremely protective Against Breast
Cancer the next risk factor is hormonal
birth control are oral contraceptives
oftentimes these medications are
prescribed for women who have hormonal
imbalances but rather than taking a
medication that can disrupt your
endocrine system it's better to actually
look at what's happening underneath they
can increase your risk for breast cancer
and often times these medications are
prescribed for women who have hormonal
imbalances it's actually easier to take
a deep dive into why you have hormonal
imbalances and correct them rather than
taking exogenous sources of hormones
that doesn't fix the problem underneath
and the next risk factor is of course
the brocca mutation if you have a brocca
mutation which is a mutation in a tumor
suppressor Gene that can increase your
risk for breast cancer but I have hope
for you there are things that you can do
to modulate that to impact the
expression of your braa if you do have
the mutation so when assessing breast
health screening is recommended the
common screening that most women do
would include mamography
thermography that involves looking at
the the heat changes to the breast and
checking for any differences between the
breast and this can identify pathology
we also have bilateral MRI within
without contrast we also have the
ultrasound and if there is a mass that
needs to be biopsy we can use final
aspiration and then of course self-
exams when you check your breast every
month making sure that there's no lumps
and this is what screening entails and
it's really important when you're trying
to preserve your breast tissue and
monitor for any changes in your breast
tissue now this model can be very
helpful in identifying any pathology of
the breast and it's usually recommended
because you're screening for cancer
you're screening for pathology and if
you can catch it early but this model
fails to address the subset of patients
who do not have cancer but are
experiencing changes in their breast
tissue that precedes breast cancer women
with benign diseases such as cyst breast
pain fibrocystic breast are often told
we ruled out cancer so your symptoms are
normal folks just because a vast
majority of women have these symptoms
does not make it normal and often times
they say you have these symptoms here if
it bothers you take oral contraceptives
or tamoxifen women are left with no
solutions to their problems and are
vulnerable to tissue changes that are
happening in their breast that could be
warning signs not to ignore so
maintaining breast health means paying
attention to the signals maybe you've
had a benign condition I of the breast
that's non-cancerous lumps or
fibrocystic changes these could be
warnings that the breast tissue is
changing in an unfavorable direction and
you have an opportunity to change the
disease course unlike the watch and
weight approach you can take action well
before something develops and is
detectable on routine screening i' like
to give an example of a patient who went
in for mamography one year and they told
her we see something but we're not quite
sure what it is so come back next year
and that entire year she did nothing
they gave her no recommendations to
follow that entire year she went back
the next year for her mamogram and sure
enough the report showed that she had
breast cancer perhaps lifestyle
recommendations dietary recommendations
recommendations on how to change her
environment to reduce her toxic burden
perhaps this would have changed her
disease course leading to better outcome
but that didn't happen sadly but here on
true health I am going to equip you with
the tools to help you improve your
breast health decrease your risk for
breast cancer and if you are one of
those ladies that have had some kind of
Imaging that looks questionable not
quite fit in the characteristics for
cancer but there's something going on
this is for you there's plenty for us to
do as women to change our disease
outcomes and reduce our risk here on
true Health we like to give you the
tools and we're going to start with the
loow hanging fruit so number one stay
current with breast screening is so
critical it is so important physical
exams are very important so stay current
on those things consider early detection
assays one test to consider is gallery
gallery is a multi-cancer early
detection test that detects over 50
types of cancers this is something I
offer to my patients and it's incredibly
useful it has
99.5 specificity and a low false
positive rate of 05% gallery is not
intended to replace traditional
screening but is definitely something
that you can add as an adjunct to the
existing screening you would be a
candidate for gallery if you have a
family history of any cancer or if you
have the brocca mutation or if you're
just one of those people who like to
stay ahead of your health and prevent
cancer before it develops this is the
test for you what makes this test
valuable is that it picks up cancer in
the blood by DNA that's Shed from tumor
cells sometimes IM cannot pick up
everything but with blood testing you
might be able to catch the cancer a lot
sooner maybe you're a woman who's
already had cancer you're in remission
or you've just undergone treatment
checking for early recurrence is also
important signatera is a blood test that
will detect cancer recurrence before
it's detected on standard Imaging it's
also used to assess a patient's response
to treatment if you've already gone
through treatment and you've been told
that you're in a clear you can do
signatera blood test that will help to
identify if the cancer is still present
at a molecular level in addition to
standard screening and early detection
you might consider a nutrient assessment
levels of 25 hydroxy vitamin D greater
than 45 nanog per milliliter is
associated with the 45 % decrease in
breast cancer risk other nutrients that
tend to be low in women with breast
conditions includes EPA DHA or omega-3
fatty acids GLA magnesium in fact
magnesium acts as a co-actor for vitamin
D binding protein and it supports
metabolism of vitamin D into its active
form magnesium levels need to be
adequate in order for us to properly
utilize vitamin D also also be sure to
take your vitamin D with vitamin K2
vitamin K2 is an essential vitamin that
controls the flow of calcium in the body
and therefore preventing calcification
of soft tissue with vitamin D
supplementation in order to use vitamin
D you have to make sure you have
adequate levels of magnesium and you
need to make sure that you take your
vitamin D with vitamin K2 checking for
magnesium deficiency checking for your
omega-3 concentrations checking for
vitamin D these are very important
nutrients other nutrients that tend to
be low in women with breast conditions
include B vitamins iron and iodine so
you need to check these nutrients iodine
deficiency contributes to breast cancer
and its progression iodine deficiency is
associated with fibrocystic breast
disease which can be effectively treated
or prevented with iodine supplementation
fiber cystic breast disease affects at
least 50% of women of child baren age
and is associated with an increased risk
of developing breast cancer molecular
iodine has been found consistently
useful and the promotion of breast
health regular use of molecular iodine
has been shown to reduce the sensitivity
of breast cells to the proliferative
effects of estrogen
resulting in healthy breast tissue
however word of caution talk to your
doctors before supplementing with high
high iodine supplementation and some
people can worsen oshimoto and other
thyroid diseases if you have spotting in
between periods uterine fibroids severe
painful Menses PCOS or even heavy
bleeding during your Cycles it's a sign
of hormone imbalance or estrogen
dominant functional estrogen dominance
can be due to low progesterone Andor
excessive exposure to xenoestrogens from
our environment or poor hormone
detoxification so checking urinary
hormone metabolites can be helpful for
assessing imbalances and assessing for
any hormones that might be in excess or
deficiency when it comes to breast
health assessing estrogen breakdown
products can be of value when estrogen
is broken down into the liver there are
three routes that estrogen can take one
route is more protective than other RS
and we call it the good the bad and ugly
the two hydroxy form of estrogen so when
estrogen is in our body and it goes
through the liver it can be broken down
into a metabolite called to hydroxy this
metabolite is very protective it has
very little binding Affinity to estrogen
receptors in fact in a Petri dish
they've been able to show that it
decreased cell proliferation by 20 to
30% in cultured breast cancer cell lines
so that's encouraging we know that when
estrogen is broken down it's the two
hydroxy form that we want to
preferentially push estrogen into the
next one is the bad we have four hydroxy
metabolites so when estrogen's broken
down it can conver into for hydroxy that
is associated with an increased risk for
breast cancer it's more reactive and
considered less safe so we want to make
sure that we're not producing a
tremendous amount of four hydroxy
metabolize of estrogen and then we have
the ugly the 16 hydroxy form an
estrogenic molecule that activates
estrogen receptors and it creates it can
create DNA mutation s and induced
proliferation of breast cancer cell
lines in a Petri dish by 40 is the 16
hydroxy it activates estrogen receptors
creates DNA damage and it induces
proliferation the next form of estrogen
metabolite that is extremely potent and
is actually the most potent out of the
two hydroxy and four hydroxy is 16
hydroxy is very potent in its ability to
activate estrogen receptors and it
induces proliferation in cultured breast
cancer cell Lines by 40% so this is
quite concerning and this form of
estrogen we really want to eliminate but
overall it's the two hydroxy we want to
ensure that our estrogen is broken down
into and it's the four hydroxy 16
hydroxy we really want want to make sure
we do not accumulate it's important the
next important thing to do is to assess
the hypothalamus pituitary adrenal
thyroid and gatal AIS these systems work
together to maintain homeostasis of the
endocrine system and any endocrine
disruption can contribute to the
development of breast cancer or cancer
in general in addition to nutrient
testing it's important to check your por
hormones cortisol checking cortisol
levels throughout the day is very
important in maintaining overall health
high levels of cortisol is connected to
insulin resistance it also shunts
progesterone production so when we have
high cortisol it can impact other
hormones that play a role in maintaining
our overall health and reducing our risk
for cancer and breast cancer in reducing
our risk to breast cancer in any kind of
cancer checking cortisol levels
throughout the day is important for
overall health and certainly important
for breast health high amounts of
cortisol spikes insulin creates insulin
resistance and it also shuns
progesterone production balancing
cortisol levels and adrenal Health can
improve dis glycemia it's important to
get these hormones under control so that
you can mitigate the risks and you can
also just improve overall health thyroid
function is another one that's really
important the thyroid can influence
ovarian hormones women with breast
cancer are twofold more likely to
develop thyroid cancer and women with
thyroid cancer have a
67% greater chance of developing breast
cancer so ladies make sure to check out
your thyroid check out your adrenals
look at your cortisol levels make sure
sure to balance your hormones because
these hormones do interact with each
other and helping to protect the body
against cancer and most importantly
breast cancer in addition to standard
screening it's important to consider
addressing breast health biochemically
by targeting hormone metabolism
nutrition and lifestyle factors so we
talked about hormone metabolism and
hormone function and assessing urinary
estrogen metab hormone and assessing
urinary hormone metabolites the two
hydroxy the four hydroxy the 16 hydroxy
estrogen metabolites and other hormones
it's now time to look at nutrition
because nutrition is the Cornerstone of
our health when it comes to nutrition
first you need to think about what
things you have to remove from the diet
that's a must for breast health avoid
red meat products red meat products
contain DNA damaging chemicals such as
heterocyclic amines that are produced
when the meat is cooked at high
temperatures and what makes them very
dangerous is that they're able to
stimulate breast cancer cell
proliferation almost as pure as estrogen
so these chemicals have estrogenic
effects just like the hormone estrogen
that our bodies produce and they can
Infiltrate The ducts where most breast
cancers are formed heteros CC amines
have been shown to induce tumors of the
breast the prostate and colon and
lymphoma in animal studies
postmenopausal women with low fruit and
vegetable intake but High lifetime
intake of grilled or barbecue or Smoked
Meats but High lifetime of grilled or
barbecued or Smoked Meats have a
47% higher odds of breast cancer R meat
consumption also increases igf1 a potent
amplifier of estrogen receptors so if
you want to protect your breast tissue
avoid eating red meat and cooking red
meat at very high temperatures due to
the carcinogenic effects of heterocyclic
amines on the breast tissue deep frying
oils deep frying oils promote high risk
of metastasis and breast tissue avoid
frying folks is very easy the reason why
is frying in oil creates oxidative
stress because we're changing the
chemical makeup and forming more toxic
chemicals and when we create more
oxidative molecules that promote
oxidative stress it leads to tissue
damage and for that reason if you want
to protect your breast and improve
breast health and reduce your risk for
breast cancer avoid deep frying in oil
what are the things you should eat this
is really important cruciferous
vegetables I talk about cruciferous
vegetables all the time they're a very
potent class of functional foods that
have powerful phytochemicals that can
influence estrogen metabolism Endo 3
carbinol is a phytochemical of
cruciferous vegetables that can induce
the cyp 1 A1 a phase one enzymes
involved in liver detoxification and it
can increase that two hydroxy remember
the two hydroxy I talked about that is
what we want we want to favor our two
hydroxy pathway when estrogen is broken
down and cruciferous vegetables can Aid
in that cruciferous vegetables can also
inhibit that four hydroxy the bad
estrogen metabolite i3c
supplementation has been shown to
increase the two hydroxy and AD do ad
dois 300 to 400 milligrams per day so if
you're having a problem with eating
cruciferous vegetables you can
supplement with i3c But be sure to talk
to your doctor another powerful
phytochemical inside cruciferous
vegetables is seane I talk about seane
all the time sephor aane is a potent
inducer of face to metabolism in a liver
triple negative breast cancer represents
the poorest prog no is among all breast
cancers amongst all breast cancer
subtypes with no available effective
therapy triple negative breast cancer is
a type of cancer that lacks estrogen
receptor progesterone receptor and two
this means that the cancer is not driven
by hormones most cancers can be easily
inhibited by blocking estrogen and
progesterone receptors but not in a case
of triple negative breast cancer this
makes it a very difficult cancer to
treat when solid tumors form as in a
case of breast cancer cancer stem cells
also known as tumor initiating cells are
released from the tumor cancer stem stem
cells share several characteristics of
normal tissue stem cells and have been
identified in human tumors as possessing
long-term selfrenewal potential and
resistance to chemotherapy and radio
theapy this explains why cancer comes
back a second time or often times is
more aggressive or metastic there are no
effective treatments available targeting
cancer stem cells however there's an
affordable accessible and more cost
effective option than traditional
chemopreventative drugs however there's
an accessible and more cost effective
option than traditional
chemopreventative drugs and a study
published in a journal of cancer
prevention research scientists
demonstrated that sephor Fane and
cruciferous vegetables can inhibit cell
proliferation and the formation of
cancer stem cells and triple negative
breast cancer so ladies There's Hope for
women with this dreaded disease or
currently battling triple negative
breast cancer just a little tip before
cooking your cruciferous vegetables chop
them and wait 20 to 40 minutes to allow
the release of sephor aane sephor aane
is heat stable but not the enzyme
myrosinase that releases sephor famee
chopping and waiting a bit before
cooking gives this enzyme the
opportunity to help release sephor Fane
if waiting is not an option add powdered
mustard seeds to the vegetable after
cooking to increase the amount of sephor
aane in a food if you have difficulty
tolerating Brasa family veget vegetables
again you can supplement with sorane as
you could with i3c as our biological and
chronical age increases important tumor
suppressor genes the most common the
broca and repair genes work less
efficiently and can downregulate given
rise to cancer when braa becomes mutated
the likelihood of developing hormone
sensitive cancers rise exponentially in
fact your risk for developing breast
cancer if you in fact if you have the
broca one or braa 2 mutation your
lifetime risk of developing breast
cancer is 82% breast cancer risk by age
50 among mutation carriers born before
1940 was 24% the good news is that 10%
of breast cancer is due to genetics but
what changed between the 194 40s and
today the environment toxic exposure
dietary practices Agriculture and stress
the list goes on in fact in vitral
studies in fact have demonstrated that
toxin exposure May contribute to silenc
in braa one so definitely our
environment influences epigenetic
expression but what if I told you there
was a way to protect braa genes are even
reverse the effects toxins have on braa
micronutrients and nutritional
bioactives with antioxidative properties
help reduce oxidative stress caused by
toxic estrogen metabolites and these
nutrients include vitamins a e c we also
have anoco sytin which is very powerful
at helping it because of his antioxidant
capabilities turmeric or curcumin
egcg lopine alphalipoic
acid and flavonoids these are potent
nutrients that help to reduce and
mitigate any oxidative stress that is
caused from toxic estrogen metabolites
that four hydroxy I talked about that 16
hydroxy these nutrients can help quench
the effects of these reactive estrogen
metabolites Resveratrol is the next
nutrient it is very powerful
antioxidant and it's found in all of our
colorful fruits and veggies our red and
purple grapes our blueberries our
cranberries and more it can in fact
reverse the effects that toxins have on
broca which is amazing however it does
have estrogenic effects Resveratrol if
you are a woman with a history of
estrogen sensitive cancers such as
breast ovarian and uterine cancer
it's important not to supplement with
resveratrol but rather get it from
dietary sources Resveratrol and
supplement form exceeds the amount
that's found in our fruits and veggies
and for that reason it's best to get
your Resveratrol from dietary sources if
you are a person who has a history of a
hormone sensitive cancer egcg is awesome
of a phytochemical founding green tea
and has been shown in one study three
cups of green tea per day was associated
with up to 37% reduction in breast
cancer and recurrence egcg has
antioxidative properties as well as
anti-carcinogenic properties Against
Breast Cancer you don't have to drink
green tea but you can supplement with
egcg talk to your doctor the next
important food to consider to maintain
healthy breast tissue is soy now I know
it gets a bad rep but Soy is important
soy contains isof bones that have
protective effect against toxin induced
braa 1 and braa 2 expression soy isolab
bones also modulate estrogen receptors
and Metabolism in fact soy consumption
is associated with a reduced risk of
breast cancer and postmenopausal women
it's also been shown to be effective
against other cancers has been demonized
because of the potential estrogenic
effects of soy however is well
established that there are health
benefits to consuming healthy very well
sourced soy when sourc and soy makes
sure it's organic as most conventionally
grown or as most conventional soy is
genetically modified and is sprayed with
glyphosate preferably fermented soy such
as temp
miso tamari NATO all of these are great
options for soy another class of food
that's important for maintaining breast
health is fiber daily excretion of
urinary estrogen metabolites is lowered
by dietary fiber in a pilot study of 45
premenopausal women at high risk for
breast cancer researchers found that
administration spons of two tablespoons
of flax seeds da for one year resulted
in fewer precancerous changes in the
breast an 80% participants had a drop in
their levels of
ki67 a biomarker for cell proliferation
so fiber is incredibly important inside
flax seeds a group of phytoestrogens
that have weak estrogenic activity
suppress the proliferation of breast
cancer cells lignin are found in a
variety of plant foods such as pumpkin
such as flax seeds pumpkin seeds sesame
seeds soybean broccoli and some berries
in another study women who ate more than
six grams of soluble fiber per day which
is the equivalent of one cup of beans
had an 85% lower risk of breast cancer
another study estimated every 20 gram of
fiber intake per day was associated with
a 15% lower risk of breast cancer
mushrooms High dietary intake of
mushrooms is shown to decrease breast
cancer risk and pre and postmenopausal
women by 64% compared to women who do
not eat mushrooms white button mushrooms
are potential breast cancer chemo
preventative agents as they suppress
estrogen production and therefore mimic
similar mechanisms as tamoxifen used to
treat estrogen sensitive breast cancer
don't worry if you don't like white
button mushrooms you can supplement with
a mushroom powder that has white button
mushrooms a lifestyle practice that you
can incorporate that can significantly
reduce your risk for cancer would be
fasting animal studies demonstrate that
prolonged fasting positively influences
cancer development and metabolic
processes that are associated with risk
and prognosis of breast cancer
researchers from the University of
California San Diego among other
California universities found that
fasting for 13 hours a day May reduce
the risk for breast cancer recurrence
and death from the disease in fact
short-term fasting May enhance
anti-tumor effects of doxy rubison a
chemotherapy agent in fact short-term
fasting May enhance the anti-tumor
effects of certain chemotherapy agents
such as doxy rubesin sleep you have to
get sleep under control ladies and men
if you want to protect your health and
protect yourself from cancer all tissues
of the cells of the human body are under
circadium rhythm in a region of the
brain called the hypothalamus sits the
master clock that regulates the
physiology of the cardiovascular system
digestion that regulates the physiology
of cardiovascular function digestion and
absorption the microbiome pulmonary
function eating sleeping behavior and so
much more circadium rhythms maintain
tissue balance during the 24-hour day
night cycle circadium clocks play
fundamental roles in cell division DNA
damage responses and Metabolism
circadian disruptions have been proposed
as as a contributing factor for cancer
initiation and progression acute sleep
deprivation decreases DNA repair gene
expression and promote DNA breaks and
damage acute sleep deprivation decreases
Gene repair mechanisms and promote DNA
breaks and damage did you know your
breast tissue is also under circadium
Rhythm meaning that healthy breast
tissue performs certain functions within
a 24-hour period And when a circadium
clock is disrupted it affects the
physiology of the breast promoting
abnormal changes in the breast tissue
researchers at the University of
Manchester compared breast tumors to
normal breast tissue and found that
breast tumors had alter circadium clocks
compared to normal tissue they also
found increased tissue stiffness around
the tumor alter circadium clocks play a
role in the development and progression
of breast cancer factors that disrupt
circadian rhythm shift work jet lag
stand up Lads the use of stimulant such
as caffeine irregular eating patterns
excessive eating late night eating lack
of physical activity avoidance of early
morning sunlight exposure and artificial
light exposure at times when we're
supposed to sleep exercise is so
important it helps to Mo move and
mobilize those toxic estrogen
metabolites out of our body 5 hours per
week a vigorous aerobic exercise can
lower estrogen and progesterone exposure
by 20% exercise lowers circulating
estrogen levels walking an hour a day
has been shown to be more associated
with significantly lower risk of breast
cancer and environment we have to assess
our environments ladies if you want to
maintain your breast health it's
important to look into your assess your
environment for toxic exposure Organo
chlorine pesticides can activate cyp
enzymes responsible for producing that
16 hydroxy form of estrogen that we
talked about so if you have a problem
with estrogen dominance consider
assessing your exposures to Xeno
consider doing a thorough assessment of
your toxin EXP exposure it's really
important for maintaining breast health
in a journal of clinical Obstetrics and
Gynecology black women who routinely use
chemical hair straighteners had a two to
three times higher risk of fibroids out
of the 7,000 women diagnosed this is
alarming this is an example of how
chemical exposure can increase your risk
for hormone sensitive conditions and
fibroids if you didn't know have tons of
estrogen receptors so assessing your
environment for toxin exposure is really
important for maintaining overall health
to prevent cancer or any type of
condition that's causing an imbalance
because these chemicals are known as
endocrine disrupting chemicals they can
disrupt your hormone system and create
problems chemical exposure from products
used on the body found in our food and
water supply or in the air that we
breathe can promote changes to our
physiology and initiate a Cancer and in
this case for breast cancer awareness
month we are talking about breast health
and these chemicals are known to
facilitate the initiation of breast
cancer ladies take a look at your
environment and make sure that you're
reducing your exposure to xenoestrogens
LIF cell dietary and environmental
factors s are major contributors to the
development of breast cancer in fact 80%
of breast cancer is due to environmental
factors knowing this you can now be
proactive about addressing your
modifiable risk factors to maintain
healthy breast tissue and prevent breast
cancer improve response to active
treatment if you're currently undergo
treatment or to remain in remission
hopefully this information presented
today is encouraging thank you for
tuning in to True Health Tuesday be sure
to click on the link in the description
box for your free guide to breast health